Today's צ"ו tzadi vav 96 and we're the
16th day of the עומר, Omer, second day of ראש חודש אייר.
Rosh Chodesh Iyar. We pick up at the top of
thank you I don't know we pick up at the top of
צ"ו עמוד א' tzadi vav amud aleph and the issue had been
whether you make a ברכה bracha of בורא פרי הגפן Borei Pri
HaGafen on store-bought wine you know the type of quality that's sold
in the store which the גמרא Gemara calls כוסא דשותא kosa deshot
with a קוף koph not a כף chaf which means basically like
starting to sour. And as we'll see in a minute what it's
going to mean the assumption is it's going to be identified
with wine that starts smelling vinegary but it still tastes like wine.
Sort of like milk you know? Yeah that's a good point you
smell the milk I didn't think about that that's a good analogy.
You smell the milk to see if it's still good even though
when you taste it the taste might still not be that off.
Of course the funny thing is I assume people know like half
of what you taste is about smell because you know it's not
just your taste buds it's that the aromas go up the back
of your mouth through your nasal cavities which is why when you
have a cold food doesn't taste as good.
But okay so this is beginning to smell like vinegar it's souring
but it still tastes like wine that's what the גמרא Gemara is
going to identify with it. So do you make בורא פרי הגפן
Borei Pri HaGafen or not which is a way of saying is
it still called wine? And the argument is of course you know
I mean. אביי Abaye asked רב יוסף Rav Yosef this question and
רב יוסף Rav Yosef said he said which how do you פסקן?
pasken? And רב יוסף Rav Yosef said look I have a ברייתא.
braita. Okay so let's take a look at the ברייתא. braita. Okay
so now we're at the top of צ"ו עמוד א' tzadi vav
amud aleph or if you want to do we'll do the last
line of צ"ה עמוד ב'. tzadi hey amud bet. אמר ליה אביי
לרב יוסף Amar leh Abaye leh-Rav Yosef so אביי Abaye said to
רב יוסף Rav Yosef הא רב יהודה הא רב חסדא. Ha-Rav Yehuda,
Ha-Rav Chisda. רב יהודה Rav Yehuda and רב חסדא Rav Chisda they
have their different positions what ברכה bracha you make. מר כמאן סבירא
ליה Mar keman sevira leh how does the master hold? אמר ליה
מתניתא ידענא Amar leh: Matnita yedana I know a ברייתא. braita. What's
the ברייתא? braita? Top of צ"ו עמוד א'. tzadi vav amud aleph.
We taught in a ברייתא braita הבודק את החבית להיות מפריש עליה
תרומה. Habodek et hachavit lihyot mafrish aleha truma. Okay
you separate you have a barrel which as you're going to be
taking תרומה truma and maybe מעשרות ma'asros or whatever from all of
your other wine you're going to constantly say okay there's another you
know another whatever three barrels of wine so whatever a tenth of
a barrel is. Is that right? Ten percent of three barrels is
three if you had three barrels right you're taking the third no
no ten percent of three barrels is a third of a barrel
right?
Not really it's less.
Okay whatever it doesn't matter we'll do it easier. But whatever it
is okay you're taking in more wine and you're basically saying the
now this new wine that I just took another הפרשת תרומה hafrashas
truma on this new wine that we just pressed is in that
barrel that we set aside. Then you do then you take in
a week later you press more wine okay the next הפרשת תרומה
hafrashas truma on this next one is in that barrel that we
set aside. Okay and you keep on doing that. And then eventually
you're keeping track eventually that barrel will be all תרומה truma and
then you'll give it to a כהן. kohen. All right but you
have to make sure that the barrel is going to remain wine
as you continue to do this because you can't use vinegar for
הפרשת תרומה hafrashas truma on wine. So you check the barrel at
the beginning to make sure that it's wine you see that it's
wine and then this is the barrel that you're going to slowly
be designating more and more parts you know over a period of
time to be תרומה truma from this barrel. So that's what you
do. Wait the other way around let's say all your wine becomes
vinegar? Well that would be true. But you know you yeah that's
a good question. But I assume you see the wine as you're
being מפריש. mafrish. The barrel's already barreled up. הבודק את החבית להיות
מפריש עליה תרומה Habodek et hachavit lihyot mafrish aleha truma so you
check the barrel because you want to use this barrel to over
a period of time be designating different you know small little parts
of the wine in it for תרומה. truma. ואחר כך נמצא חומץ
V'achar kach nimtza chometz and then when you're finally done and you
have a barrel full of תרומה truma as far as you know
and you open it up to give it to a כהן kohen
you find that it's turned vinegar. Okay so the question is it
started you know six months ago as wine. When you open it
up six months later it was vinegar. At what stage do you
have to be concerned that it definitely turned vinegar it might have
turned vinegar because and what stage can you assume like so if
you did right
if here you were there's January 1st and it's and here's your
barrel and you tasted it and it's wine. And then here's June
1st and you open it up and it's vinegar. Okay and along
that way you know you did a הפרשה hafrasha
here הפרשה hafrasha here you did a הפרשה hafrasha here here here
here and here. Okay and you want to know when was it
wine definitely wine and definitely those things were good. good, the תרומה
Truma from those from here each one of these has a different
section has a
different group of barrels that you're doing the הפרשה Hafrasha on. So
you want to know which of these הפרשות Hafrashas was definitely good
and it was definitely wine and these barrels will be okay. Which
of the הפרשה Hafrasha was definitely bad and it was definitely vinegar
and therefore the הפרשה Hafrasha was no good and you have to
do it again? And of course the worst case scenario is that
it's a ספק. Safek. Because then you have to do it again
and both of them are תרומה Truma because it might have already
been תרומה Truma but it might not and you have to do
it again. So you want to know which of these הפרשות Hafrashas
are definitely good, which are definitely bad, and which are a ספק.
Safek. When was it assumed it was still wine, when do we
know it definitely had become vinegar, and when was there a doubt?
That's the issue. Yes. What matters for תרומה Truma is when you
put it aside, not when it ultimately gets to the כהן? Kohen?
Exactly. Exactly. If it spoiled when it got to the כהן, Kohen,
it's unfortunate for the כהן, Kohen, but the act of הפרשה Hafrasha
was good. That is correct. Wait, let me say it was vinegar,
then you're מפריש Mafrish it and you sold it to me, then
it turns out it wasn't a good הפרשה. Hafrasha. Yeah. Then what
is my status? Okay, you're an אנוס Anus or whatever. You're a
what? No, you're an אנוס. Anus. I assume you're an אנוס. Anus.
Yeah. Do you have to
pay double? Yeah, but you were an אנוס, Anus, you had a
right, you go by חזקה. Chazaka. We tested it, it was wine,
a חזקה Chazaka it would have remained that way, you were relying
on חזקה, Chazaka, so yeah. Okay, so now let's see what the
source. Now by the way, I just should point out a little
interesting footnote.
An interesting little footnote, which is the רשב"ם Rashbam wants to know,
how did you test to see that this was still that this
tasted like wine and it was good? It was טבל Tevel when
you tested it. So you're not allowed to eat טבל. Tevel. So,
right? How did you test this barrel? You only מפריש תרומה Mafrish
Truma on stuff that's טבל, Tevel, right? So this barrel is טבל
Tevel and then slowly small pieces are being designated as תרומה, Truma,
okay, but how did you taste it? You're מפריש Mafrish when you
taste? Oh, so the רשב"ם Rashbam says, all right, you take a
little bit, you מפריש Mafrish a little from this little bit and
then you taste it. That's what the רשב"ם Rashbam says. תוספות Tosafot
says, you didn't really taste it, you just smelled it. Okay? So
anyway, all right, but anyway, moving on. Okay, it says like this.
הבודק את החבית והוא מפריש עליה תרומה והולך ואחר כך נמצאת חומץ.
Habodek et hachavit vehu mafrish aleha truma veholach ve’achar kach nimtzeit chometz.
And then it was vinegar. כל ג' ימים ודאי. Kol gimmel yamim
vaday. The first three days it's definitely X, that's X. מכאן ואילך
ספק. Mikan ve’eilach safek.
From that point on it's a doubt. מאי קאמר? Mai ka’amar? So
what does that mean? What do you mean the first three days
it's ודאי? Vaday? So which three days? ודאי Vaday what? אמר רבי
יוחנן הכי קאמר. Amar Rabbi Yochanan hachi ka’amar. This is what it
means. כל ג' ימים הראשונים ודאי יין. Kol gimmel yamim harishonim vaday
yayin. The first three days here, from January 1 until January
3,
these three days you know it's יין. Yayin. You know if you
tasted it and it was wine, it's not going to become vinegar
within three days. So this three days it's
ודאי, Vaday, ודאי יין. Vaday yayin.
After that period you don't know. Maybe after three days from tasting
it, it started to go bad or turned into vinegar. Three days
before? Well, that's going to be the alternative. מכאן ואילך ספק. Mikan
ve’eilach safek. After that point all of this period up to the
last day until how many days are in May?
31. Up to May 31, he says, all of this he says
is ספק. Safek. The only day you know that it's definitely vinegar
is June 1. So you know for three days you were safe,
you know the rest of the time you have no idea whether
it became vinegar, and the only day it's ודאי Vaday not good
is June 1. Okay, that's how he reads it. All right, so.
כל ג' ימים הראשונים ודאי יין מכאן ואילך ספק. Kol gimmel yamim
harishonim vaday yayin mikan ve’eilach safek. מאי טעמא? Mai ta’ama? Now what's
the reason? חמרא מעילאי אקר. Chamra me’ilai akar.
So first, we're assuming that you tasted it, you tasted from the
top of the barrel. We're also going to assume that when wine
goes bad, it starts going bad at the top. I don't know
why we assume that but okay. So it's going to start, so
meaning that if there was a problem, if it was already in
the process, you would have tasted it. You would have known. That's
why it's important to know top or bottom, whether it's possible the
process had begun without your being aware. So you tasted it and
at the time you tasted it, it was totally okay because had
it started going bad, it would have started from the top and
you would have tasted something. מאי טעמא חמרא מעילאי אקר. Mai ta’ama
chamra me’ilai akar. It starts going bad from the top. והא טעמיה
ולא אקר. Veha ta’amei velo akar. And you tasted it and it
hadn't turned. אם תמצי לומר בתר דטעמיה אקר. Im timtzi lomar batar
detamei akar. If
now, let's say, so what would you say? As soon as you
finished tasting it, the souring process began a second after you finished
tasting it. That's like the worst case scenario. הוה ריחא חלא וטעמא
חמרא. Havei reicha chala veta’ama chamra.
Now when the souring process begins, at the beginning of the souring
process, it smells
When you tasted it, it tasted fine and it smelled fine. If
it started going bad a second later, so that would mean that
it had begun smelling like vinegar, it wouldn't yet taste like vinegar.
Okay, and it would have taken apparently three days for that process
to complete and for it to now taste like vinegar.
So therefore the second after I tasted it, let's say it started
going bad, it started smelling like vinegar. Now, if we say that
even when it's going bad and smelling like vinegar, smelling getting worse
worse worse worse, yet it tastes like wine, so if we're saying
that it's ודאי vadai okay here, we mean in this going bad
period where it's smelling like vinegar and tasting like wine, it's still
considered wine. And that's why the first three days is okay. And
therefore according to this approach, you'd make a בורא פרי הגפן borei
pri hagafen when it smelled bad, when it was souring, but it
still tasted, but it was still not sour. So ריחא חלא וטעמא
חמרא, rei'acha chala ve-ta'amecha chamra, anything that smells like vinegar but still
tastes like wine, חמרא chamra is still wine. Okay, so according to
him, why is this ודאי יין? vadai yayin? Because the worst case
scenario is that it is
souring, as soon as you know, here it's perfect, here it's perfect,
so worst case scenario is after this, it starts souring, which is
smell like vinegar and taste like wine, okay, and therefore even in
that case, it's good for three days. All right, so that shows
you, and therefore until at the end of three days, it actually
tastes like vinegar. So that shows you that souring wine is still
considered wine according to this position and that's why the first three
days is still, is still ודאי vadai okay. But what about the
other approach? They're all ספק. safek. No, but weren't we doing to
the barrel anything? You weren't opening it. You knew there was 100
ounces in the barrel and you were doing 100 of תרומה terumah
at one ounce at a time. But why did we not require
you to just open the barrel every so often? Because then it
would spoil the wine or whatever and normally you go by חזקה.
chazakah. The principle is you're allowed to rely on חזקה. chazakah. It's
just here it turned out bad. No חזקה chazakah wine would never
turn into vinegar? I don't know, but you're normally allowed to go
by חזקה. chazakah. Okay, and we don't want to, why should we
go to that effort? No חזקה chazakah wine would ever turn into
vinegar? Well that's questions of חזקה עשויה להשתנות chazakah asuya l'ishtanot etc.
But normally not, in good most cases, no. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says like this.
Okay. Okay, so that's, that's Rabbi Yochanan's position. Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi
says no, the opposite. כל גמל ימיא אחרונים ודאי חומץ. kol gimmel
yamim acharonim vadai chometz. No, no, no, no, no. These last three
days, he says, I guess we'll draw him where we, we already
used green, too many colors here. These last three days, he says,
these three days, okay, these three days he says according to this
position, that's considered ודאי חומץ. vadai chometz. Okay, now how do you
know that? Right, the question you should be asking is, is that
just because it's vinegar here, maybe it finished a process? Maybe it
only started turning vinegar in these last few days and now you
tasted it and it was vinegar. So what allows us to assume
that it was ודאי vadai vinegar three days ago? So the גמרא's
Gemara going to say what allows us to assume that is what
did we say the process of becoming vinegar is? That it takes
three days of souring, right? So if it takes three days of
souring, so if we assume that here it's definitely vinegar, it must
have taken at least three days of souring, and he's calling that
vinegar. So you see that he holds that during the souring process,
when it tastes like, smells like vinegar and tastes like wine, it's
also, it's already considered vinegar. Okay, and therefore back here, even if
it started a second, it would already be a ספק, safek, right?
The ספק safek vinegar begins immediately because as soon as the souring
process begins, it's already a ספק safek vinegar. It's already vinegar. So
for him here, it definitely began and it's ודאי vadai vinegar, and
any day thereafter day one, it might have begun and therefore it's
a ספק safek vinegar. So he says in the souring process it's
vinegar, and he says no, during the souring process it's wine. Let's
just read this in the גמרא. Gemara. It says like this. Okay.
כל גמל ימיא אחרונים ודאי חומץ. kol gimmel yamim acharonim vadai chometz.
מכאן ולהלן ספק. mikan ul'halan safek. Backwards
it's ספק safek even starting on day one. מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama,
what's the reason? So here the גמרא Gemara throws in something which
is like a little, a little superfluous, which the תוספות Tosafot say
it didn't have to say.
חמרא מתתאי עקר. chamra mitatai aka.
Wine actually starts going bad not at the top but at the
bottom. ואימא עקר ולאו אדעתיה. ve-eima akar ve-lav adaita. So number one,
when you tasted it on day one, maybe it had already started
going bad and you weren't aware because you didn't, you were tasting
the top of the barrel. But that's not really the argument and
that's not relevant for our purposes. The real point is the next
line. ואם תמצא לומר מעילאי עקר, ve-im timtza lomar mealay aka, even
if we should assume it starts going bad from the top and
you tasted it, meaning so on day one it was totally
fine. And you tasted it and it was completely fine,
okay, but a second after you finished tasting it on day one,
it started going bad. Now starting going bad, the souring process is
הוי ריחיה חלא וטעמיה חמרא, Havi reikhei khala veta'imeih khamra, it smells
like vinegar and it tastes like wine, וריחיה חלא וטעמיה חמרא חלא,
Verekhei khala veta'imeih khamra khala, and therefore that's vinegar. So here the
ספק safek for him starts on day one because it might have
started souring and that's vinegar, and the ודאי vaday is the last
three days because the last three days it was part of the
souring process and therefore it's definitely vinegar. So here the גמרא Gemara
very nicely says based on two possible reads of this ברייתא brayta
we have our answer. Either
depending on whether you read the ברייתא brayta the first three days
or the last three days, it tells you whether the during the
souring process is it considered wine or vinegar. Of course the question
is רב יוסף Rav Yosef right, since he gave the answer to
אביי. Abaye. אביי Abaye said, how do you פסקנ'ן pasken during the
souring process, is it wine or vinegar? He says well I got
the ברייתא. brayta. So of course it's very nice, but how do
you read the ברייתא? brayta? So the גמרא Gemara is going to
ask that. Which way did רב יוסף Rav Yosef actually read the
ברייתא? brayta? Okay, but anyway, one way or another, the answer is
hidden in this ברייתא. brayta. It just depends on how you read
it. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this, before we get
to how רב יוסף Rav Yosef actually פסקנ'ן, paskened, the גמרא Gemara
says like this,
okay. דרומאי, Deromay, the ones from the south, presumably south Israel, מתנו
משמיה דרבי יהושע בן לוי, matnu mishmei de-Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, they
taught a ברייתא brayta in the name of רבי יהושע בן לוי
Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi that both the last three and the first
three are ודאי. vaday. ראשונים ודאי יין אחרונים ודאי חומץ. Rishonim vaday
yayin acharonim vaday chomets. The first three are definitely wine, the last
three are definitely vinegar. Now make up your mind, right? How does
that work? If the souring process it's still wine, how do you
know this is ודאי vaday vinegar? If during the souring process it's
vinegar, how can you assume that this is definitely wine here? Maybe
the souring process began. So the גמרא Gemara says אמצעי ספק, emtsa'i
safek, it's the middle that's ספק. safek. הגופא קשיא, Hagufa kashya, one
minute, there's no that's not consistent. אמרת ראשונים ודאי יין, Amarta rishonim
vaday yayin, the first three days is definitely wine, אי ee presumably
meaning even if the souring process began right away, אמר ריחיה חלא
וטעמיה חמרא, amar reikhei khala veta'imeih khamra, if it smells like vinegar
and tastes like wine, חמרא, khamra, it's still wine.
והדר אמרת אחרונים ודאי חומץ, Vahadar amarta acharonim vaday chomets, the last
three days are definitely vinegar. So how's that possible? Maybe it only
started maybe it only became vinegar a minute ago. אלמא alma it
must be that you think that during the souring process it's vinegar.
אמר ריחיה חלא וטעמיה חמרא חלא. Amar reikhei khala veta'imeih khamra chala.
So when it starts smelling like vinegar it's vinegar. That's why the
last three days are ודאי vaday vinegar. So make up your mind,
which one is it? So the גמרא Gemara says כגון דאשתכח חלא
סיפתקא. kegon d'ishtakach chala sipatka.
You found some סיפתקא חלא. sipatka chala. No you found you found
סיפתקא sipatka somehow means very, very vinegary vinegar. Okay, I don't know
where it comes from. Anyway, strong vinegar. So when you opened up
the barrel here, it was like really vinegary. So there is no
doubt in your mind that it had become fully vinegar at least
three days ago. During the souring process it's wine, but this vinegar
is so strong that it had to have been fully vinegar at
least three days ago. Like pickles, you know, the really sour pickles.
There you go. Okay, there you go. דאי לאו דאקר תלתא יומי
לא הוי משתכח חלא סיפתקא, De-ee lav d'akar telata yomei la havi
mishtakach chala sipatka, if it had not become fully vinegar at least
three days ago,
you would not have found such strong vinegar. Okay fine, but at
the end of the day the גמרא's Gemara saying he basically holds
that during the souring process it's wine. So now רב יוסף Rav
Yosef said to אביי, Abaye,
look it's a ברייתא. brayta. Great, which way did he read the
ברייתא? brayta? So גמרא Gemara says כמאן פשיט ליה, keman pashit leh,
which way did רב יוסף Rav Yosef sort of you know conclude
for אביי Abaye what the הלכה halacha was based on the ברייתא?
brayta? How did he read the ברייתא? brayta? So גמרא Gemara says,
so guess what, it's a debate how he read the ברייתא. brayta.
פליגי בה רב מרי ורב זביד חד אמר כרבי יוחנן וחד אמר
כרבי יהושע בן לוי. Pligi bah Rav Mari ve-Rav Zevid chada amar
ke-Rabbi Yochanan ve-chada amar ke-Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi. Okay,
one position said he read it like רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and
the other one said that he read it like רבי יהושע בן
לוי. Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi. So therefore so we don't know which
way he concluded. During the souring process is it wine or is
it vinegar? Anyway רשב"ם Rashbam says since even the last position of
the דרומאי Deromay in the name of רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi
Yehoshua ben Levi in principle holds that during the souring process it's
wine, the רשב"ם Rashbam thinks that the conclusion is that it's wine
during this souring process. Okay, but anyway but that's the question. Is
it considered wine? What ברכה bracha do you make? And when it's
in this souring process, could you be מפריש mafrish from this onto
תרומות ומעשרות? trumos u'maasros? Is it considered wine on wine or vinegar
on wine and that's the question of how to read the ברייתא.
brayta. Okay now we go to another point which is obviously related.
איתמר המוכר חבית יין לחבירו והחמיצה. Itmar hamocher chavit yayin lachavero vechimitsa.
Ah,
now it's getting interesting.
I sell
Mike my a barrel of wine, he takes it home, he keeps
it in the same barrel because there's going to be discussion later
if he put it in a different barrel maybe it would be
maybe it was his jugs, maybe he ruined it, but here it's
in the original barrel it was as he got it and then
he tastes it and it's vinegar. He tasted it in the store
and it was wine. Then a few days later he tastes it
at home, it's vinegar. vinegar. So is that a מקח טעות? mekach
taut? Did I sell him souring wine? The assumption is right remember
we had a
משנה Mishnah before, if you are מוכר יין ונמצא חומץ, mocher yayin
venimtzah chometz, it's a מקח טעות. mekach taut. The assumption here is
that the same would be true if it was already in the
process of souring. Okay, right imagine you bought some milk from the
store, like I think I like that example with the milk and
you took it home and it was already smelling bad. It didn't
yet taste bad but it was already smelling bad, like you want
your money back. You're expecting to buy something that is not in
the process of going bad. So the question here is but wine
sometimes goes bad. And maybe I sold it to him, it was
totally fine and it only started happening once it became his. So
the question of is it a מקח טעות mekach taut or not
is at the moment of sale, at the point of sale, was
it already souring or not? That's the question. He tasted it right?
He had to have tasted it at the store, is that right?
תוספות Tosafot and the רשב"ם Rashbam assume the scenario is that you
did taste it. Okay, if you didn't, they'll talk about that in
a minute. Okay. So, איתמר, itmar, המוכר חבית יין לחברו והחמיצה, hamocher
chavit yayin lachaveiro vehachmitzah, and then it became and then it became
vinegar. אמר רב, amar Rav, כל ג' ימים הראשונים ברשות מוכר. kol
gimmel yamim harishonim birshat mocher. The first if it became vinegar within
the first three days then as we said before it takes three
days for it to become vinegar, then you know that it began
it had already begun to sour under my under when it was
when I had owned it before I sold it to you at
the point of sale it was souring. Ah, we're assuming although not
in the גמרא Gemara that you tasted it. Okay, so you know
you didn't you don't have a great palate. You didn't detect it.
But nevertheless we are certain that if it becomes vinegar within three
days the process you know if it becomes vinegar the process began
three days ago. So it turns out and nobody is misleading anybody,
it happens sometimes, right? It turns out that I sold you wine
that was already spoiling and
therefore מקח טעות. mekach taut. And you get your money back. Okay.
מכאן ואילך ברשות לוקח. mikan va'eilach birshat lokeach. After three days it
is in the it's your property, right? Maybe the whole process began
when after you sold it and therefore you don't get your money
back. You can't say מקח טעות. mekach taut. Now pause, okay? Because
here becomes the question of like maybe we should say it's a
ספק. safek. It went bad after four days. So within three days
we know it definitely began three days ago, at least three days
ago, right? But if it went bad four days, you know do
we know it definitely it never takes longer than three days to
go back right? I mean if if on the fourth day you
taste it and it was vinegar, it's still possible it had already
started when it was under when I sold it to you. So
why isn't that an issue? So תוספות Tosafot says here's why it
matters that Michael tasted it. This is what תוספות Tosafot says. If
Michael tasted it in the store and as far as he could
tell it tasted fine and it only started going bad four days
later then we're going to assume it was totally fine and it
and it all happened after Michael bought it. However, if Michael didn't
taste it and after four days he tasted it and it was
vinegar, then it's a ספק. safek. And right and in that case
the תוספות Tosafot says the principle would be המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה.
hamotzi mechaveiro alav hara'ayah. If you've already paid me the money for
it then tough luck buddy, you go prove that it was it
was bad when I sold it to you. If you hadn't paid
me for it yet then I would then you could say I'm
assuming it was bad when you sold it for me and make
me take it back. Okay so that's the way תוספות Tosafot says.
It's not clear in the גמרא. Gemara. But the idea is within
three days it definitely began under my you know when when when
I sold it, it was already in the process. If it took
more than three days it's from from if after three days you
tasted it and not took more, after three days you tasted it
and it was bad there's the way this is the way תוספות
Tosafot reads it there's a doubt, it's possible it's possible whatever. After
three days wait say that part again. After three days if after
three days it was bad, okay then we don't know when the
process began, right? You know maybe it was bad three days ago
and you only tasted it on the fourth day, who knows what?
So there's a ספק safek what happened. So there תוספות Tosafot says
that's when had you tasted it in the store we would assume
it was ודאי vadai good. Had you not tasted it in the
store we'd have to deal with the question of המוציא מחברו עליו
הראיה. hamotzi mechaveiro alav hara'ayah. Do you use it later? What? Do
you use it later? I don't know, there's got to be some
limit obviously. Anyway that's the basic point. The basic point is is
that we use the three days to determine whether it was ודאי
vadai bad when it was sold at the point of sale or
not, ודאי vadai in the process of souring. ושמואל אמר uShmuel amar
that's the first position. ושמואל אמר uShmuel amar now שמואל Shmuel says
חמרא אכתפא דמריה שוור. chamra akatpa demarei shavar.
Wine is sort of carried or thrown on the on the on
the shoulders of the owner. Okay that's clear. What does that mean?
So the רשב"ם Rashbam basically says like it's your מזל mazal if
wine goes bad. You know there's some type of a metaphysical belief
or whatever we're going to quote a פסוק pasuk later that basically
you know that I don't know maybe it's seen as like wine
is sort of represents the person, I don't know what it is,
but if the wine goes bad we say that was your bad
luck, it was due to somehow your מזל. mazal. So therefore even
within the first three days Michael got it and it was bad
within the first three days I could say you know what Michael,
I don't I'll tell you some... For example, like at home we
have this thing that whenever it comes to like anything about electronics,
okay, you know דבורה Dvora's trying to deal with it or whatever
like like you know it's never working. I deal with it, I
push the exact same buttons she pressed and it works. So it's
like, you know, somehow the machines like me and don't like her.
That's at least the way it feels. Okay, so I say, Michael,
I don't know, somehow the wine with me it was never a
problem. All of a sudden it gets to your house, it goes
bad in three days, I'm going to assume that there's something to
do with your מזל, mazal, even if you didn't change anything, same
bottles or whatever, it's this belief of your מזל mazal was going.
We don't say that for the כהן Kohen though. The place they
gave it to the כהן Kohen is תרומה truma and then. No,
no, no, here I opened it, I didn't give it to the
כהן. Kohen. Let's say you had. All right, I don't know, maybe.
I don't know. Anyway, that's anyway it's a different question of if
מקח וממכר mekach umimkar is the same as איסור. issur. Anyway, that's
what שמואל Shmuel says. שמואל Shmuel says you cannot claim מקח טעות,
mekach taut, you're going to assume you can't prove, you can't assume,
you know, that it was, that it was even within the first
three days, it was your מזל. mazal. תוספות Tosfos does not like
that answer for various reasons, and תוספות Tosfos has a has a
has a very nice different read of the phrase חמי אקשא דמרי
שוור. chama aksha d'marei shvar. תוספות Tosfos says maybe it was totally
fine in my store. How did it sour in less than three
days? You carried it home! When you carried it home on your
shoulders, that unsettled it. And therefore it's, therefore it wasn't souring. Yes,
it was חומץ chomets in two days later, that's because of how
you transported it. What if it was bad if I didn't take
it home yet, like in the store and I came back three
days? Right, that would be a נפקא מינה. nafka mina. And of
course תוספות Tosfos also asks, I don't get it, when I'm selling
wine, presumably I know that it has to be transported home, so
why don't, you know, why doesn't it sort of my liability as
it were incorporate the likelihood that it would go bad? But first
of all you could say maybe I say to Michael, you could
have handled it with more, you know, more, you know, with more
care. How do I know how you handled it? And anyway even
if that's true, when I sold it, it was not already souring.
It was totally fine when I sold it. So that's what שמואל
Shmuel says. Even within the first three days, it's not
a
מקח טעות. mekach taut. But רשב"ם Rashbam and תוספות Tosfos both assume
that the case in the גמרא Gemara is that you tasted it.
But it doesn't mean at the purchase, meaning if you're the seller
and you say it's fine I can't rely on that right? Maybe.
I don't know, that's a good question. Okay, but anyway, but it
was tasted. And the buyer ever tasted? That makes his case—according to
שמואל Shmuel you mean? According to even רב. Rav. Well according to
רב Rav I'd say because I don't even because what do you
mean? If I taste it and it's vinegar who wants to שלעפ
schlep this wine home and then come in and return it or
whatever? When you buy something in a store, right, you sort of
look at it or whatever. You know if it's bad when you
get it home they'll accept it back and you'll be able to
return it. But who wants to bother? Right? So you want to
be as confident as you can that you're buying good wine. So
but תוספות Tosfos and רשב"ם Rashbam both say that that's the case
and that's why, you know, the default assumption here is that it
was a good sale and the buyer has the burden of proof
that it was a bad one. So רב Rav says that that
burden of proof is satisfied in the first three days. And שמואל
Shmuel says no, if again assuming—it's not said in the גמרא—but Gemara
assuming it was tasted at the time, even within the first three
days you cannot say that the wine was souring. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara says like this: אמר רב יוסף עובדא כוותיה דרב
בשכרא וכוותיה דשמואל בחמרא. Amar Rav Yosef uvda kavatei d'Rav b'shichra u'kavatei
d'Shmuel b'chamra. So רב יוסף Rav Yosef פסק paskened in a practical
case like רב Rav in a case of beer, of שכרא, shichra,
that he said that within the first three days he let the
guy return it, okay, then it was bad, but by שמואל Shmuel
by wine, by חמרא, chamra, that even if it was bad in
the first three days he didn't let the guy return it. Now
what's the reason to make a distinction? So according to the רשב"ם,
Rashbam, the distinction might be, it would probably might be that I
don't know, could be how he feels how long does it take
beer to sour. Maybe that's part of the difference. Maybe part of
the difference is maybe מזל mazal only affects wine, מזל mazal doesn't
affect beer. You know, so the, you know, it's not exactly clear
why he split his vote, but the גמרא Gemara says הלכתא כוותיה
דשמואל. hilchata kavatei d'Shmuel. Apparently we rule like שמואל Shmuel whether it's
beer or it's wine and we say even if it's bad right
away, you can't return it. Again, why is that? Do we say
it's because of the transport? Do we say it's because that that
made it bad? Do we say it's because of this מזל mazal
idea? Okay, that's not clear. Thankfully at least I know some of
our stories here don't, I don't know, kosher butcher, you take it
home, you open it up and it smells and it's clearly bad,
they'll take it back. You know. If it was clear it was
bad for me to start with. Yeah, so obviously not. I mean
if part of the reason is because of, you know, some of
this is מציאות metzius based. How long does it, you know, do
we assume your tasting was a good tasting or not? How long
does it take to sour? Do we think that say, you know,
how do we assume that transporting affected it? Right, so therefore, you
know, those are, so all of those are. factors. And that's presumably
also to distinguish between beer and wine. But at least the גמרא
Gemara says in the case it's dealing with, we're going to assume
like שמואל Shmuel that you cannot return it. And again, רשבם Rashbam
and תוספות Tosfos both say it was a case that in the
store you tasted it and it was fine. Okay, תנו רבנן. Tana
Rabbanan. So now that was so there we had a moment of
returning to the major theme of בבא בתרא, Bava Basra, which was
sales and מקח וממכר, mekach umimkar, מקח טעות, mekach taus, at least
this פרק. perek. But now we go back to a ברכות Berachos
theme. Okay? We were discussing before what ברכה bracha you make on
souring wine, so let's take a look. תנו רבנן. Tana Rabbanan. אחד
שיכר תמרים ואחד שיכר שעורים, echad sheichar temarim ve'echad sheichar se'orim,
whether it is a beer or mead derived from dates. That's mead,
right? Isn't that what mead is? It's like it's date honey? Date
what? You have like Agave? No.
I don't know, but mead, mead is like the classic drink of
the ancient world and I think it was basically fermented date honey.
I'm pretty sure. Someone can look it up. What? You'll look it
up. So whether it is a type of a beer, whatever, derived
from dates, whether it is derived from barley, which is our beer,
okay? ואחד שמרי יין, ve'echad shimrei yayin, or you take the, you
know, the dross of the wine, what's it called, the lees, you
know, the shells after they've been pressed, the skins, and you put
water in a barrel with them, and it gets some of the
wine flavor, okay, or some of the grape flavor. So these cases,
מברכים עליהם שהכל נהיה בדברו. mevarchim aleihem shehakol nihiya bidvaro. The ברכה's
bracha
שהכל. shehakol. Meaning that as opposed to what? You don't make a
בורא פרי העץ borei pri ha'etz on the mead honey, on the
mead, you don't make a בורא פרי האדמה borei pri ha'adama or
בורא מיני מזונות borei minei mezonos on the beer even though it
came from barley, and you don't make a
בורא פרי הגפן borei pri hagafen on the grapey water even though
it came from grapes, okay? And all of the reasons are
well, grape juice is different. Well, yeah, exactly. Although grape juice is
a hundred percent grape juice. This is grapey water, okay? Grape flavored
water. So it's grape drink. It's not grape juice. Anyway, so all
these reasons is because those ברכות brachos so בורא פרי הגפן borei
pri hagafen is the easiest one to explain. It's not יין, yayin,
okay? It's water with a little wine with a little grape flavor.
Now we're going to discuss in a minute, like you can water
down wine and it's still בורא פרי הגפן, borei pri hagafen, okay?
But
this has way too little of a proportion of actual grape juice
in it. This is that's easy why that's not wine. Okay. Why
is the fruit thing not בורא פרי הגפן? borei pri hagafen? It
derives from a fruit. So the the mead, the mead, the thing
that comes from the what? I'm sorry, what did I say, הגפן?
hagafen? בורא פרי העץ, borei pri ha'etz, thank you. Why is it
not בורא פרי העץ? borei pri ha'etz? It derives from a fruit.
So the הלכה halacha is, is that it has to be what's
called נשתנה למעליותא. nishtaneh le'maliusa. That something to get a בורא פרי
העץ, borei pri ha'etz, if it's not in the original form that
it grew, it has to be considered to be in a better
form. Not, and if you do a change which is based on
some halachic principles, you know, considered to be a lower form of
it, then it loses the בורא פרי העץ borei pri ha'etz ברכה.
bracha. And the general assumption is, is that fruit juices other than
יין, yayin, שמן, shemen, and what's the other one?
Wine and oil, grape no, that's it, יין yayin and שמן. shemen.
Other than wine and oil, any other fruit juices other than wine
and oil are basically considered to be like what the גמרא Gemara
says, like you know, just
like זיעה, zei'ah, like I don't know, like משקה, mashkeh, like it
doesn't have the same weight. Like for example, on שבת, Shabbos, if
you do סחיטה, sechita, you squeeze, you know, something to get the
liquid out of it, right? You squeeze a grape to get out
grape juice, you squeeze an olive
to get out olive oil, right? That's, you know, that's like the
case that you're ודאי חייב vadai chayav on שבת. Shabbos. Everything else
is like debatable because how significant, you know, is the fruit juices.
Fruit juices are like I know, I'll talk about these days in
a minute. So in the גמרא, Gemara, other than יין yayin and
שמן, shemen, all fruit juices were seen to be of a very
like inferior quality, it's not the normal thing that people drink, it's
not, you know, it's a lower form of the fruit. Okay, that
was the גמרא's Gemara general assumption. And therefore you don't make a
בורא פרי העץ borei pri ha'etz in this case. Now, that's very
interesting because what happens when it's not a lower form of the
fruit? So for example, nowadays, all the type, you know, all orange
juice you buy comes from a certain type of a species of
oranges, what? Juice oranges, that are, you know, that are like whatever
hybrid, bred specifically for the purpose of turning them into juice. So
the highest form of the fruit, I mean the purpose of the
fruit, you know, it's like its mission in life is to become
juice. So clearly that's the highest form of the fruit. So
you
should be making
If you make
your
own orange juice at home with like oranges that are not, so
that probably would would not be the same because then because because
no because because then if the if the if the orange itself
is not of the species מין min that specifically for orange juice
then we would still apply the general principle that oranges are primarily
eaten. So to turn it into juice would be an but I
don't know it's an interesting question. Let's say the practice I live
in South Florida everybody's got their their orange trees in their backyard
and people basically don't eat it everybody is a health nut and
they're always squeezing it in the morning for whatever for orange juice.
So I don't know how much like the common practice which it
might change it. I know that the arguments about contemporary orange juice
and chocolate is because it's specifically grown for that purpose so that
makes it almost like indisputable that that should be considered to be
the highest form of it. But if it's not grown for the
if it's not the מין min that's grown for that purpose but
it's the practice in this area I think it's more of a
question. All that is based on the premise that fruit juice is
inferior but now that you know I so I understand that your
kids a בוודאי bevada you know it shouldn't even be a question
but I'm saying even these days you know juice bars are all
over the place. Right even if it's not even if you're equal
like you know it's not any worse. So I think that so
I think it's not just a question of better or worse it's
also you know the ברכה bracha is בורא פרי העץ. borei pri
ha'eitz. It refers to directly relates to a פרי. pri. Now obviously
this derives from a פרי. pri. So the point is when the
thing is not in its original form the ברכה bracha is immediately
less less relevant. Okay I mean people you know because בורא פרי
העץ borei pri ha'eitz I mean when I say that on orange
juice I'm going to call this פרי העץ? pri ha'eitz? I'm going
to chocolate פרי העץ? pri ha'eitz? It comes from פרי העץ pri
ha'eitz right? So the ברכה bracha is immediately less relevant when it's
not in its original form and therefore it requires the נשתנה למעליותא
nishtana l'malyusa you know the argument that this is really the form
of this fruit is this way. So just because it's common to
do it I don't think that that's sufficient okay because part of
the problem is it starts with if it's not in its original
form you probably should be making שהכל. shehakol. Does everyone agree to
eat the juice orange you still make a עץ eitz or do
you just make it directly and not even do it? Oh that's
interesting. I think everybody would still say עץ eitz yeah. I think
in its original form is like the default and when it changes
the argument then has to be made why it still makes that
ברכה. bracha. Okay the case by the way of beer is even
more interesting. So number one it's a similar argument it's not you
know the original form and it's not clearly like you know the
classic use of this or whatever not clearly an improvement I should
say not not classic not clearly improvement but the other thing about
beer is that it's mostly water okay so that you know so
how much is that really considered the thing itself that's similar to
the wine case. By the way it's very relevant we just finished
with פסח. Pesach. What is the status of grain alcohol for חמץ?
chametz? There are three positions about it. Some say it's חמץ גמור
chametz gamur some say it's completely מותר לכתחילה mutar l'chatchila don't tell
anybody whatever we don't פוסק pasken but some say it's basically water
it's not חמץ chametz it's water it's you know any any juices
it gets from the grain that's meaningless or whatever and others put
it in like a middle category like a type of a חמץ
נוקשה chametz nukshe type of a category or תערובת חמץ ta'aroves chametz
is probably the better category. Anyway okay so here it says the
ברכה bracha you make is שהכל נהיה בדברו. shehakol niyeh bidvaro. So
the גמרא Gemara says like this רבא ורב יוסף דאמרי תרוייהו Rava
v'Rav Yosef d'amri t'vayehu now הכי אמרי achaim amim excuse me I
skipped a line הכי אמרי achaim amim others say
by the way let's just read this one short תוספות Tosfos זה
אחד שכר שעורים zeh echad sheichar se'orin cause it sort of distills
the point I was saying. He says oh I didn't even think
about that okay I often make puns without realizing it because that's
where my mind is going. Okay זה אחד שכר שעורים zeh echad
sheichar se'orin so says דלא אישתני לעלוייא d'lo ishtani l'iluya number one
the barley what the second oh no the first is זה אחד
שכר תמרים zeh echad sheichar t'marim the second is זה אחד שכר
שעורים zeh echad sheichar se'orin דלא אישתני לעלוייא d'lo ishtani l'iluya number
one is the barley did not clearly get improved by this transition
דאיכא עילויה קרינא בפת d'iska iluya karina b'pas the best form of
it is to make it into bread. Of course when you make
it into bread, you're not going to be saying בורא פרי האדמה
borei pri ha'adama anymore, you're going to be saying המוציא. hamotzi. ועוד,
ve'od, דמי יימר דסערי עיקר דלמא מיא עיקר. de'mi yeimar de'sari ikkar
dilma maya ikkar. What makes you think that this is fundamentally about
barley? This is really water. It's really a type of, you know,
flavored water. Okay. So, okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this. And I'll read one line of the previous תוספות Tosfos because
it's also important about the point I was telling you about fruit
juices. ואחד שכר תמרים ve'echad shechar temarim so go back שהכל. shehakol.
לאו דוקא שכר תמרים אלא אפילו דבש תמרים lav davka shechar temarim
ela afilu devash temarim מברך עליו שהכל. mevarech alav shehakol.
So even if you were to straight eat the actual honey, right?
מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? כי דאמר ki de'amar before you had to
sort of ferment it or whatever and added water, etc. Right? It
was just straight the derived juices that essentially like is date juice
as it were. מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? Like date—some honey oozed out
and I still make שהכל? shehakol? Yeah, yeah, exactly, you know, you
didn't add water, you didn't ferment it, it's the straight juices. מאי
טעמא? mai ta'ama? Like orange juice. כי דאמר בכיצד מברכין אמר מר
בר רב אשי ki de'amar be'Keitzad Mevarchin amar Mar bar Rav Ashi
האי דובשא דתמרי—this hai duvsha de'tamrei date honey—מברך עליו שהכל. mevarech alav
shehakol. מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? זיעה בעלמא הוא. zei'a be'alma hu.
It's just like, you know, sweat. והיוצא מן הפירות קרי זיעה. vehayotzei
min hapirot kari zei'a.
Okay, and that's considered like sweat. Okay. And then, interesting if you
want to hear a dissenting opinion, ולא כמה שפירש בהלכות גדולות ve'lo
k'mo shepeirash be'Halachot Gedolot דהיינו דוקא התם דטרייהו במיא. de'hainu davka hatam
de'taryeihu bemaya. It's only because water was added. אבל דייב מתמרי aval
dayyiv mitmarei if
it directly came, flowed from the date, like, you know, straight date
juice, like straight orange juice, מברך עליו בורא פרי העץ. mevarech alav
borei pri ha'eitz. He says, and then תוספות Tosfos says that's not
true. Okay. So here's this whole idea that A, fruit juices are
generally dismissed and not treated as important, point number one. And point
number two, in general, if it's not in the original state, it
doesn't get that core ברכה beracha unless it's נשתנה לעילויא, nishtana le'iluya,
unless it's sort of is improved. Alright, so that's some of the
basic principles here. So now—did the case of improve again? Like what?
Well first of all, when barley or wheat turns into bread, you
know, you make a מזונות mezonos or מזונות, mezonos, you make a
מזונות, mezonos, I mean it's not the same ברכה, beracha, but it
doesn't go down to שהכל. shehakol. It's actually like a higher form
of a ברכה. beracha. Munch on barley?
What? Go just and munch on—yeah, well if that would be דרך
אכילה derech achila like parched barley or whatever like roasted barley, you'd
make a אדמה. adama. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this. So רבה ורב יוסף Rabba ve'Rav Yosef okay, אחרים אומרים, acherim
omrim, others say, מים שיש בהם טעם יין מברך עליו בורא פרי
הגפן. mayim sheyeish bahem ta'am yayin mevarech alav borei pri hagefen. No,
if the water actually has a winey taste, okay, then you would
still make a בורא פרי הגפן. borei pri hagefen. Winey or almost
like—has to be winey or let's say it's a grapey—that's a question,
what's טעם יין ta'am yayin mean? Right, does that have to be
wine, does that have to be grape? You know, but okay, it's
not exactly defined. Now let's see what the גמרא Gemara does with
it. רבה ורב יוסף דאמרי תרווייהו Rabba ve'Rav Yosef de'amri tarveihu אין
הלכה כאחרים. ein halacha k'acherim. We don't פוסקן pasken that way. Even
if it's got that taste, it's still—it might have a wine taste,
but it's still water with a wine taste. It's a wine
drink, it's not wine. Okay. אמר רבא amar Rava דכולי עלמא, de'chulei
alma, everybody would agree, now we're going to sort of frame what
exactly the debate is between the אחרים acherim and the תנא קמא.
Tanna Kamma. דכולי עלמא, de'chulei alma, everybody would agree, רמא תלתא ואתא
ארבעה, rama tlata ve'ata arba'ah, if you put in three units of
water into these—with these, you know, these lees, and then out of
it came—you extracted four units of grapey water. So that means that
you have a full unit of grape juice you were able to
extract from the lees. Right? You understand what happened? You put in
three ounces of water into this barrel
with this—with these, you know, wine skins, grape skins, you let it
sit there for a while, and then you pour it out and
now you got four ounces. So where'd the extra ounce come from?
It came from grape juice. So a quarter—so the—so now you have—you
have a quarter grape juice or whatever unfermented wine, three—three units water,
that's wine. So everybody would agree in that case, רמא תלתא ואתא
ארבעה, rama tlata ve'ata arba'ah, חמרא הוא, chamra hu, that's wine. רבא
לטעמיה, Rava le'ta'ameih, Rava goes according to his reasoning. Grape drink that
is a quarter grapey right and three quarters water you would make
בורא פרי הגפן. borei pri hagefen. דאמר רבא de'amar Rava כל חמרא
דלא דרי על חד תלתא מיא לאו חמרא הוא. kol chamra d'lo
dari al chad tlata maya lav chamra hu. Any wine that doesn't
have three units of water to one unit of wine is not
real wine. So—so three units is certainly still considered to be wine,
even three units of water. Everybody would agree to that. רמא תלתא
ואתא תלתא, rama tlata ve'ata tlata, let's say you put in three
ounces of water in the barrel and then you poured it out
and you poured out three ounces of now grapey water. So everybody
would agree ולאו כלום הוא, velav klum hu, then you can't assume
there's any significant amount of grape juice in the water. Okay. כי
פליגי, ki pligi, and everybody would agree even the first opinion—even the
אחרים acherim that you don't make בורא פרי הגפן. borei pri hagefen.
Maybe it has a little grapey taste, but there's no significant amount
of grape juice, everybody would agree you do not make a בורא
פרי הגפן. borei pri hagefen. כי פליגי, ki pligi, what's the debate?
דרמא תלתא ואתא תלתא ופלגא. de'rama tlata ve'ata tlata u'palga. You put
in three ounces of water and then you poured out three and
a half. So the question is, now you know definitely there's some
non-trivial amount of grape juice, at least a half an ounce of
grape juice is mixed in the water. Do you assume only a
half
an—
The full three ounces of water that went in were the three
ounces that came out. פשלי פלגא, pashle palga, so the only thing
extra is a half an ounce. Okay, so you've got a half
ounce of grape juice and three ounces of water, which is a
half ounce to six half-ounces. It’s a one to six ratio, right?
ופלגא בשישה פלגי, u-palga be-shisha palge, a half, you know, mixed with
six halves, a half of an ounce mixed with three ounces
מיא בעלמא, maya be-alma, six half-ounces of water, ולא כלום, ve-lo klum,
that's just grape-flavored water, that's not wine. It needs to be a
one to three ratio in order to be wine. Okay, so we're
only going to assume a half of an ounce of grape juice,
and therefore it's a one to six ratio and it's not wine.
ואחרי סברי, ve-achere savri, but the other position holds, תלתא הוו תרי
ופלגא נפיק. tlata havuh tere u-palga nafik. No, I'm going to say
in this case that I know some real grape juice came out,
I'm going to say even more grape juice came out. I'm going
to say
that of the three ounces of water that came in, two and
a half ounces came out, a half got left inside the grapes,
inside the you know the grape skins, ופש לו כוזא, u-pash lu
kuza, and therefore what you're left with is like כוזא's kuza like
a cup, I don't know why it says it, but it basically
means one ounce of grape juice is now mixed in it. So
even though you put in three and you took out three and
a half, we're going to assume the mix of three and a
half is two and a half of the original water and one
of the grape juice, or at least that's a possible mix.
Okay, וכוזא בתרי ופלגא, ve-kuza bi-trei u-palga, and one mixed into two
and a half, חמרא מעליא הוא. chamra ma’alya hu. So that's already
wine. It's not more than a one to three ratio, it's one
to two and a half, and maybe it's also tipped over by
the fact that it tastes like wine. If it's got a winey
taste and you definitely know that there's already a one to you
know at least a half unit more of grape juice, I'm going
to assume it's even more than that half unit and some of
the water got left behind and I'm going to assume that it
is wine, and that's ואחרי's ve-achere position. Okay, so that’s the debate.
So now let’s just see as the גמרא Gemara wraps this up.
גמרא Gemara says one minute, וביותר מכדי מדתו מי פליגי? u-be-yoter mi-kdei
midato mi pligi? Are you really is it really true that their
argument is when more came out than went in? Meaning maybe when
more came out than went in maybe everybody should agree it's okay.
והתנן, ve-ha-tenan, we taught in the משנה Mishnah by מעשר, ma'aser, המטמד
ha-metamed ונתן מים במדה, ve-natan mayim be-midah, המטמד ha-metamed is exactly what
this process is, it's adding water to grape skins and getting some
grapey juice grapey water out of it, and you put a measure
of water in ונתן מים במדה ve-natan mayim be-midah ומצא כדי מדתו.
u-matza kedei midato. You put X units in the barrel with the
grape leaves and you took out, you know, with the grape skins
and you took out the exact same amount. Exactly the case we
said before. What did we say before? Before we said in that
case everybody says it's water and not wine, right? Remember? We said
when it was the same amount you took out, everybody agrees that
there's not enough grape juice and it’s not wine. So גמרא Gemara
says פטור, patur, so the משנה Mishnah says okay, you’re exempt from
taking like you know from תרומות ומעשרות, trumot u-ma'asrot, okay, because that
is basically not considered to be wine, it's water. Okay. רבי יהודה
מחייב, Rabbi Yehuda mechayiv, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says you’re obligated. עד
כאן לא פליגי אלא בכדי מדתו. ad kan lo pligi ela be-kedei
midato. Now that argument is only when it was the same amount.
But presumably אבל ביותר מכדי מדתו, aval be-yoter mi-kdei midato, the implication
of that is that if more than the amount you put in
comes out, it sounds like everybody would agree that it's wine and
you have to take תרומות ומעשרות. trumot u-ma'asrot. גמרא Gemara says no.
הוא הדין דאפילו ביותר מכדי מדתו פליגי. hu ha-din de-afilu be-yoter mi-kdei
midato pligi.
Really the רבנן Rabbanan who say it’s not wine when it’s the
same amount that comes out, they would even say even more than
the same amount it would not be wine. והא דקא מפלגי בכדי
מדתו, ve-ha de-ka miflegi be-kedei midato, so why were they arguing when
it was the same amount? להודיעך כוחו דרבי יהודה, lehodi’acha kocho de-Rabbi
Yehuda, to tell you that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is so מחמיר
machmir that even if the exact same amount that went in came
out, he’s already going to consider it that that might be wine
and obligate you to take מעשר. ma'aser. Because it absorbed some, clearly
some it got flavored, and once it got absorbed some, we’re going
to have to be concerned that it might have absorbed enough and
it might actually be be wine for מעשר. ma'aser. Okay, but we’re
going to say that in our issue, in our case you know
about the question of the ברכה, bracha, right? Maybe by מעשר ma'aser
the רשב"ם Rashbam says maybe רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is more מחמיר
machmir by מעשר, ma'aser, but by the question of the ברכה bracha
we’re going to say that everybody agrees when the same amount came
out it’s definitely we’re going to treat it as water and when
a full extra unit out of three came out it’s definitely wine
and the debate is when it’s somewhere in the middle. Okay, before
we end this I’ll just read you one line here. If you
look at תוספות, Tosafot, אין הלכה כואחרי, ein halacha ke-achere,
Michael always likes to ask what the הלכה halacha is, so תוספות
Tosafot says אמר רבנו תם amar Rabbeinu Tam דאותו יין שעושים מן
החרצנים, de-oto yayin she-osim min ha-chartzanim, I also always like it's interesting
when you get a sense of what the life was like, you
know you get a slice of life, the wine that we now
make means from the you know the grape skins, אפילו יש בו
טעם יין, afilu yesh bo ta’am yayin, כיוון דלא רמא תלתא ואתא
ארבעה. kevan de-lo rama tlata ve-ata arba’a. Okay,
so he basically says and he discusses does it make a difference
whether you're using like the seeds or the or the skins or
whatever, but anyway, but תוספות *Tosafos* says we actually have this type
of a thing that we do nowadays, and תוספות *Tosafos* says and
we're still going to make a שהכל *Shehakol* and it doesn't matter
whether what you're using because we we פוסקן *pasken* as long as
it's not putting in three and coming out four. Because we reject
the חכם *Chacham*, right? Okay. Anyway, so now
and I'll just I'll just end with the following one one point,
which is that the idea of where
we have one more minute so let's just see the next תוספות
*Tosafos*, it's a classic תוספות *Tosafos*. כל חמרא דלא דרי על חד
תלת מיא לאו חמרא הוא *Kol chamra delo dari al chad tlas
maya lav chamra hu*. So this is Rav's position that wine classically
would get mixed with three unit three parts water. והכי אמר בריש
מוציא יין *Ve-hachi amar be-reish Motzi Yayin*, כוס של ברכה *kos shel
beracha*, what's the שיעור *shiur* for like a כוס *kos* of like
kiddush? צריך שיהיה בו רובע רביעית *tzarich she-yehe bo rova revit*, you
have to start with a quarter רביעית *revit* of wine כדי שימזגנו
*kedei she-yimzegenu*
because now you'll mix it with water, it'll be one unit wine
three units water ויעמוד על רביעית *ve-yaamod al revit* and then you'll
have a רביעית *revit* which is the size of our you know
kiddush cup the רביעית *revit* which is like three and a half
ounces. Okay, so now תוספות *Tosafos* says וקשה *ve-kasha*, דאמר בפרק אחד
דיני ממונות *de-amar be-perek Echad Dinei Mamonos*, אל יחסר המזג *al yechsar
hamazeg*, so that's a פסוק *pasuk* which he says שאם יש שם
כ"ג כנגד סנהדרי קטנה יוצא *she-im yesh sham kaf-gimmel keneged Sanhedrei Ketana
yotze*, ואם לאו אינו יוצא *ve-im lav eino yotze*. So אחד מהם
שהוצרך לצאת *echad me-hem she-hutztarch latzet* משמע *mashma* okay אינו יוצא אחד
מהם שהוצרך לצאת *eino yotze echad me-hem she-hutztarch latzet*.
So תוספות *Tosafos* says you're here, you have a whole convocation of
the סנהדרין *Sanhedrin* of the סנהדרין *Sanhedrin* 71 people and you are
on the סנהדרין *Sanhedrin* but you know you got to go pick
up your kids from school. Okay, so are you allowed to leave
in the middle? So the הלכה *halacha* is אל יחסר המזג *al
yechsar hamazeg*. You have to leave 23 behind. Okay, so if you're
number 23, you can't leave. Okay, but if you're number 24 you
can leave. Now what does that have to do with אל יחסר
המזג *al yechsar hamazeg*? תוספות *Tosafos* says it sounds like מזג *mazeg*
is מזיגת היין *mzigas hayayin*. So it means so this seems to
reflect an idea that wine was mixed two to one, right? So
the core one third you have to leave behind 23, right, is
effectively it's a little bit less than one third of 71, but
anyway, so anyway, but okay, but he says it sounds like it's
two to one, right? So you you can take away the water
as it were but you can't remove take away from that core
remaining third. So is it two to one or is it three
to one? So תוספות *Tosafos* discusses that, but the nice point is
he's got a real nice חאפ *chap* at the end which I
wanted to read, a classic תוספות *Tosafos*, and he says like this,
he says ורבינו מנחם *ve-Rabbeinu Menachem*, if you look at it it's
like three lines before תוספות *Tosafos* ends. The line starts with where
it says סנהדרין דף ב' *Sanhedrin daf beis* in parentheses. Okay, ורבינו
מנחם פירש *ve-Rabbeinu Menachem peireish*, דדורש *de-doreish* אל יחסר המזג *al yechsar
hamazeg*, מזג בגימטריא נ'
*mazeg be-gematria nun*. Okay, מ ז ג *mem zayin gimmel* 50. So
if you have a בית דין *beis din* of 71,
okay, and you cannot lest leave אל יחסר המזג *al yechsar hamazeg*,
don't remove 50 from the 71. So you're not allowed 50 are
not allowed to leave, only 49 are allowed to leave. So 49
leave though you'll have 22 left, right? ואין בית דין שקול *ve-ein
beis din shakul*. There you go. So so 50 aren't allowed to
leave, only 49 can leave. אל יחסר מזג מן ע"א דסנהדרין נ'
*al yechsar mazeg min ayin-aleph de-sanhedrin nun*, אבל מ"ט יחסירו *aval mem-tet
yachsiru*, וישארו כ"ב *ve-yisharu kaf-beis*, ואין בית דין שקול מוסיפין עליהם עוד
אחד הרי כ"ג *ve-ein beis din shakul mosifin aleihem od echad harei
kaf-gimmel*. Okay? So I thought that was very very cute. It's אל
יחסר המזג *al yechsar hamazeg* that it's two parts water one part
wine and you can't cut into the one part wine as opposed
to our three to one, or is it a cute little גימטריא
*gematria* that you can't have 50 leave, only up to 49 can
leave. Okay? But otherwise you can go pick up your kid at
בית ספר *beis sefer*. Okay. All right, we'll end here.